To load a 1911, the magazine release is pressed,
allowing the magazine to drop out of the pistol.
Rounds are loaded and held under
the force of the magazine spring.
It's then inserted into the magwell
and secured by the magazine catch.
To chamber the first round, the
slide is pulled to the rear,
cocking the hammer and compressing the
recoil spring.
As the slide is released,the bottom edge of the breech face
strips thetop cartridge and feeds it into the chamber.
After the cartridge is chambered, the slide pushes
the barrel forward.
The barrel pivots forward andup on the barrel link.
The locking lugs onthe barrel
enter the recesses in the slide,
locking the barrel to the slide.
Withthe hammer cocked and the barrel locked,
the 1911 is ready to fire.
The grip safetyprevents rearward movement of the trigger.
When firmly grasped, the trigger can be pulled.
The trigger bar presses against the disconnector,
transferring movement to the sear.
Thesear rotates and disengages
the full cock notch on the hammer.
The mainspring pushesup on the hammer strut,
rotating the hammerforward to strike the firing pin.
The firingpin travels forward, impacting the cartridgeprimer.
The expanding gases from the powder
charge propel the bullet through the barrel.
The recoil forces the slide back, and the barrelto unlock.
The extractor grips the rim of the
spent cartridge case
extracting it from thechamber.
As the slide continues to the rear,
the casing makes contact with the ejector,
forcing it through the ejection port.
As the slide comes back, the hammer is cocked,
andthe hammer strut again compresses the mainspring.
The sear spring presses against the sear,
which bears against the hammer.
The searfirst passes the half cock notch,
which acts as afail-safe in the unlikely event
of the full cock notch failing.
It then engages the full cocknotch,
holding it in the cocked position.
The disconnector prevents the sear from releasing
the hammer while the trigger is squeezed.
The sear spring pushes the disconnector
into its upward position when releasingthe trigger.
This allows the1911 to be fired once again.
When the hammer is cocked,
thethumb safety can be engaged,
preventing rearward movement of the slide.
On the inside portion of the thumbsafety,
is a stud.
The stud preventssear and hammer movement
if the trigger is pulled.
Once the final round of ammunition has been fired,
the magazine follower pushes up on the
slide stop, locking the slide open.